Finding Aid to the Ayako Nakauchi Kataoka Family Photograph Collection
The Bancroft Library
Ayako Nakauchi Kataoka family photograph collection
approximately 1900-1995
The Bancroft Library
Kataoka, Ayako
BANC PIC 2022.010
1800 photographs in 11 albums, 1 box and 2 oversize folders: chiefly gelatin silver prints and color prints; various sizes
Collection documents multiple generations of the family of Ayako Kataoka (née Nakauchi) (1917-1995), a Japanese American woman born in Los Angeles who was interned in the Heart Mountain Relocation Center during World War II.
Conditions Governing Access
Negatives (NEG(5x7) box 1): UNPROCESSED. UNAVAILABLE FOR USE.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ayako Nakauchi Kataoka Family Photograph Collection was purchased by The Bancroft Library from James Arsenault and Company in 2021.
Scope and Content
Collection documents multiple generations of the family of Ayako Kataoka (née Nakauchi) (1917-1995), a Japanese American woman born in Los Angeles who was interned in the Heart Mountain Relocation Center during World War II. Collection includes snapshots, portraits, photograph albums, postcards and other materials. Individuals depicted include Ayako, her husband Takeo Kataoka (1917-1984), her father Tamotsu Nakauchi (1888-1968) and mother Kaneju Miyaji Nakauchi (1890-1958), her twin daughters Kimiye and Kikuye Kataoka (b. 1957), and numerous other family members, friends and associates. Most photograph albums contain snapshots of everyday activities, family life and socialy outings, and studio portraits of family and friends. One album (vol. 2) documents Ayako's life during her internment at Heart Mountain Relocation Center (Wyoming). Another album (vol. 11) is dedicated to glamour portraits of movie stars, mostly from Japan in the 1940s through 1960s. Collection also includes material pertaining to Ayako's daughter Kimiye, the last family member to own the collection. Collection includes many photographs taken by the studio of Tōyō Miyatake, including a panoramic group photograph taken at the 1958 funeral of Ayako's mother in Los Angeles (shelved in --G folder).
Heart Mountain Relocation Center (Wyo.) -- Photographs; Japanese Americans -- California -- Los Angeles -- Photographs; Japanese American families -- California -- Los Angeles -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japanese Americans -- Photographs; Japanese Americans Forced removal and internment, 1942-1945 -- Photographs; Motion picture actors and actresses -- Portraits; Japanese Americans -- Portraits
- Photograph albums
  - Volume 1, approximately 1930-1940; BANC PIC 2022.010--fALB v.1; 185 photographs (Volume 1 (fALB))
    Scope and Content
    Chiefly studio portraits of friends of Ayako, many of them inscribed to her. Also includes studio portraits of Ayako, and a few snapshots depicting friends and leisure outings.
    Note
    Identified photographers: Tōyō Miyatake; Izuo.
  - Volume 2, 1943-1945; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.2; 115 photographs (Volume 2 (ALB))
    Chiefly snapshots pertaining to Ayako's internment at Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Wyoming, during World War II. Well-captioned throughout, the album documents Ayako's friends, family and other internees, most of whom are identified by name. Views includes individuals, groups and camp buildings. Also includes a few views taken during outings from the camp to Basin and perhaps other nearby locations. Also includes a few postcards. Many leaves are lacking previously mounted photographs and postcards.
  - Volume 3, approximately 1900-1968; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.3; 180 photographs (Volume 3 (ALB))
    Studio portraits and snapshots chiefly pertaining to the youth and early years of the marriage of Ayako's parents, Tamotsu Nakauchi and Kaneju Nakauchi. Some portraits predate the couple's departure from Japan. Later snapshots include homes and domestic scenes (pets, plants, gardening, etc.)
    Identified photographers: Motoyoshi (San Francisco), Harry Shirao (Hollywood).
  - Volume 4, approximately 1934-1968; BANC PIC 2022.010--fALB v.4; 100 photographs (Volume 4 (fALB))
    Album chiefly pertains to the funerals of Ayako's mother Kaneju Nakauchi (d. 1958) and father Tamotsu Nakauchi (1968). Also includes at least two scenes from the funeral of Masayuki Nakauchi, Ayako's brother who died in infancy in 1934. Also includes snapshots of family homes, pets, plants, friends, etc.
  - Volume 5, approximately 1935-1968; BANC PIC 2022.010--fALB v.5; 335 photographs (Volume 5 (fALB))
    Album of snapshots and portraits pertaining to various periods of Ayako's life, including social and religious group portraits taken in Los Angeles in the 1930s and 1940s; domestic scenes of her parents' home; and many views of her parents' garden taken in 1958 and 1968 (the death years of her mother and father, respectively).
    Identified photographers: Tōyō Miyatake, Imada (Los Angeles), Izuo, Shirao (Hollywood), Tanaka Studio (Los Angeles).
  - Volume 6, approximately 1960-1970; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.6; 125 photographs (Volume 6 (ALB))
    Snapshots taken at Disneyland, Grand Canyon, Hearst Castle and other Kataoka family tourist destinations in California and the Western U.S.
  - Volume 7, approximately 1968-1972; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.7; 100 photographs (Volume 7 (ALB))
    Snapshots taken at Yosemite National Park and perhaps other Kataoka family outing locations in the Sierra Nevada.
  - Volume 8, approximately 1970-1975; BANC PIC 2022.010--fALB v.8; 100 photographs (Volume 8 (fALB))
    Snapshots taken during family outings in the mountains during winter and at Disneyland. Also includes snapshots of pupils and teachers at middle and/or high school – perhaps friends and associates of Kimiye Kataoka and/or her sister Kikuye.
  - Volume 9, approximately 1960-1970; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.9; 90 photographs (Volume 9 (ALB))
    Snapshots of Kataoka family pets.
  - Volume 10, approximately 1951-1995; BANC PIC 2022.010--fALB v.10; 40 photographs (Volume 10 (fALB))
    Album pertaining to Ayako and her husband Takeo Kataoka, likely compiled after Ayako's death. Includes portraits and snapshots of the couple, copies of each of their death certificates, a copy of their marriage certificate, and ephemera pertaining to Takeo's funeral and memorial services.
  - Volume 11, approximately 1930-1965; BANC PIC 2022.010--ALB v.11; 100 items (Volume 11 (ALB))
    Chiefly commercial portraits of Japanese movie stars (including Kinuyo Tanaka) and other celebrities, and a few American celebrities. Also includes commercial postcards of views in Japan.
- Other photographs
  - Portraits, snapshots and other pictorial materials, BANC PIC 2022.010--PIC
    - Ayako Nakauchi Kataoka: studio portraits, approximately 1925-1940; 7 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 1)
      Studio portraits of Ayako, a few including her parents and siblings.
      Identified photographer: Tōyō Miyatake
    - Ayako Nakauchi Kataoka and family: snapshots, 80 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 2)
      Snapshots depicting Ayako with various family members.
    - Leaves from unidentified album, 50 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 3)
      2 leaves from an unidentified photograph album, likely compiled by Ayako, containing very small photographic prints, probably from the 1930s. Leaves include hand-written captions. Some photographs are missing.
    - Miscellaneous studio portraits (mounted), 4 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 4)
      Studio portraits: Masayuki Nakauchi, Ayako's brother who died in infancy in 1934; Ayako's daughter Kikuye Kataoka shortly after her birth; Ayako's niece Karen; and Helen Yamamoto.
      Identified photographers: Tōyō Miyatake, Nursery Identi-Foto Co., Inc. and J. Edmund Watson Studios.
    - Miscellaneous studio portraits (unmounted), 6 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 5)
      Studio portraits of various friends/associates of Ayako.
    - Miscellaneous snasphots, 50 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 6)
      Snapshots of friends, associates, travels, pets, etc. Includes one snapshot of actor Errol Flynn.
    - Miscellaneous snasphots (small), 50 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 7)
      Smaller format snapshots of friends, associates, travels, pets, etc.
    - Kimiye Kataoka, 50 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 8)
      Snapshots and portraits pertaining to Ayako's daughter Kimiye Kataoka.
    - Kimiye Kataoka: friends, 13 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 9)
      Middle school and/or high school portraits of friends of Kimiye Kataoka.
    - Kimiye Kataoka: Osmond family, pen pal correspondence and a letter, 5 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 10)
      Fan memorabilia pertaining to the Osmond family collected by Kimiye Kataoka, much of it including correspondence from other fans; snapshots of an Osmond family concert; other pen pal correspondence of Kimiye Kataoka from her youth; and a letter to her written from a friend in 1999.
    - Kimiye and Kikuye Kataoka, 35 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 11)
      Snapshots depicting Ayako's daughters, twin sisters Kimiye and Kikuye Kataoka during their childhood.
    - Kimiye and Kikuye Kataoka (small), 40 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 12)
      Smaller format snapshots depicting Ayako's daughters, twin sisters Kimiye and Kikuye Kataoka, during their childhood.
    - Kikuye Kataoka, 5 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 13)
      Childhood portraits of Ayako's daughter Kikuye Kataoka.
    - Mary Jane Kataoka, 1 photograph (Pic box 1, Folder 14)
      Portrait of Mary Jane Kataoka (born 1955) taken when 6 weeks old.
    - Materials removed from albums, 5 photographs (Pic box 1, Folder 15)
      Photographs and papers that were found laid in loosely to various albums in the collection. All are marked with the volume and location where they were found.
    - Postcards, greeting cards, miscellaneous ephemera, 30 items (Pic box 1, Folder 16)
      Chiefly unused postcards, many from the Mirage resort in Las Vegas, most of which pertain to entertainers Siegfried and Roy and their tigers; other miscellaneous postcards, souvenirs, etc.
    - Realia, 15 items (Pic box 1, Folder 17)
      Hospital identification name beads for twins Kikuye and Kimiye ("Kataoka A" and "Kataoka B"); a small, flat Japanese doll wearing a kimono; and 12 O.P.A. (Office of Price Administration) World War II ration tokens.
  - Oversize portraits, 1940-1984; BANC PIC 2022.010--AX; 3 photographs (Oversize folder --AX)
    Group portrait taken at the funeral of Takeo Kataoka, 1984, in front of the Ivy Chapel, Evergreen Cemetery, Los Angeles (2 copies); wedding portrait of Fred and Louise Morimoto, 1940.
    Photographer: Tōyō Miyatake
  - [Group portrait, funeral of Kaneju Nakauchi, Evergreen Cemetery, Los Angeles], 1958; BANC PIC 2022.010--G; 1 photograph (Oversize folder --G)
  - Negatives, approximately 1960-1995; BANC PIC 2022.010--NEG(5x7); 300 photographs in 1 box: color film negatives; various sizes and formats (Neg box 1 (5x7))
    Miscellaneous color snapshot negatives, taken during the final decades of Ayako's life, most of which are duplicated among the prints.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Negatives (NEG(5x7) box 1): UNPROCESSED. UNAVAILABLE FOR USE.